<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.1//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.1/sdocbook.dtd">
<article
><articleinfo
><title
>Buyer's guide</title
></articleinfo
><para
>Once you’ve decided to commit yourself you’ll have to shop for parts. A RepRap printer consists of two kinds of parts:</para
><itemizedlist
><listitem
><para
>Printed parts for a RepRap Prusa Mendel</para
></listitem
><listitem
><para
>Vitamins or non-printed parts like nuts and bolts and electronics.</para
></listitem
></itemizedlist
><para
>Check out the RepRap Prusa Mendel <ulink
url="http://reprap.org/wiki/Prusa_Mendel"
>bill of materials</ulink
> (BOM) to get a feel of all the parts that are required.</para
><sidebar
><title
>Warning about placing your orders</title
><para
>Don't order anything before checking your planned purchases on the <computeroutput
>#reprap</computeroutput
> IRC channel. Only place your orders after the RepRap community members on the IRC channel have approved.</para
></sidebar
><section
><title
>Printed parts</title
><para
>In Europe printed parts can be sourced from nophead or arthx. Nophead sells his parts on <ulink
url="http://myworld.ebay.co.uk/nophead00/?_trksid=p4340.l2559"
>ebay</ulink
>. Arthx can be contacted on the <computeroutput
>#reprap</computeroutput
> IRC channel (his handle is arthx.) Nophead is based in the UK, Arthx in Poland.</para
><para
>For the US also check out <ulink
url="http://www.lulzbot.com/en/3-plastic-parts"
>LulzBot.com</ulink
> (based in Loveland, Colorado, USA). For both US and Europe also check <ulink
url="http://www.emakershop.com/browse/printed-parts"
>eMAKERshop.com</ulink
>, a website where RepRap community members buy and sell RepRap parts.</para
><para
>You might also want to check out the casted parts offerd by <ulink
url="http://www.2printbeta.de/product_info.php?products_id=46"
>2printbeta.de</ulink
>. These are reportedly the only decent casted parts available.</para
></section
><section
><title
>Vitamins</title
><section
><title
>Electronics</title
><section
><title
>RAMPS</title
><para
>These vendors sell RAMPS DIY and pre-assembled kits:</para
><itemizedlist
><listitem
><para
><ulink
url="http://reprapsource.com/en/shop/list/196"
>RepRapSource.com</ulink
> (based in Germany)</para
></listitem
><listitem
><para
><ulink
url="http://xyzprinters.com/23-ramps"
>xyzprinters.com</ulink
> (based in the Netherlands)</para
></listitem
><listitem
><para
><ulink
url="http://www.lulzbot.com/en/4-electronics"
>LulzBot.com</ulink
> (based in Loveland, Colorado, USA)</para
></listitem
><listitem
><para
><ulink
url="http://ultimachine.com/catalog/electronics/circuit-boards-and-kits/ramps"
>UltiMachine.com</ulink
> (based in South Pittsburg, USA)</para
></listitem
></itemizedlist
><para
>You can buy an Arduino MEGA 1280 or Arduino MEGA 2560 board from these vendors or on ebay. Also check ruben-ikmaak (<computeroutput
>info [at] ikmaak [dot] nl</computeroutput
>, based in the Netherlands) for Arduino MEGA boards.</para
></section
><section
><title
>Sanguinololu</title
><para
>These vendors sell Sanguinololu DIY or pre-assembled kits. For a small extra fee they will solder the SMD part for you, something which you should <link
linkend="sanguinololu_SMD"
> certainly not consider doing yourself</link
>. Ask the vendor directly in case no such quotation is made on their website.</para
><sidebar
><title
>Voltage regulator</title
><para
>Make sure you get the voltage regulator on you Sanguinololu. A ATX power supply usually doesn't give a clean 5V, better to get 5V for you electronics from the 12V source with a voltage regulator. If you're not sure ask your vendors.</para
></sidebar
><itemizedlist
><listitem
><para
><ulink
url="http://www.xyzprinters.com/24-sanguinololu"
>xyzprinters.com</ulink
> (based in the Netherlands)</para
></listitem
><listitem
><para
>ruben-ikmaak (<computeroutput
>info [at] ikmaak [dot] nl</computeroutput
>, based in the Netherlands)</para
></listitem
><listitem
><para
><ulink
url="http://www.lulzbot.com/en/4-electronics"
>LulzBot.com</ulink
> (based in Loveland, Colorado, USA)</para
></listitem
></itemizedlist
></section
><section
><title
>StepStick</title
><para
>Most of the vendors above carry the StepStick or Pololu boards. Be careful to actually buy the A4988 stepper drivers. The A4983 is an older chip and doesn't have overcurrent protection, the A4988 does. You will still find A4983 boards available, better avoid them.</para
></section
></section
><section
><title
>Power supply</title
><para
>You will need a ATX power supply of about 20A on the 12V channel. The current doesn't have to be higher than 20A but it shouldn't be 15A either. 20A on 12V is enough to run a RepRap Prusa Mendel 3D printer with a heated bed.</para
></section
><section
><title
>Stepper motors</title
><para
>The RepRap Prusa Mendel 3d printer uses bipolar stepper motors with four wires. The step angle should be 1.8°<footnote
><para
>See the <ulink
url="http://reprap.org/wiki/StepperMotor"
>RepRap wiki page on stepper motors</ulink
> for more details.</para
></footnote
>.</para
><para
>The SY42STH47-1684A is the ideal stepper motor for a RepRap Prusa Mendel 3D printer because the Pololu stepper drivers can bring out its maximum torque. You want as much torque as possible on your 3D printer. These stepper motors are available from <ulink
url="http://www.zappautomation.co.uk/product_info.php?cPath=9_43&amp;products_id=516"
>Zapp Automation</ulink
> (based in the UK.) Also check ruben-ikmaak (<computeroutput
>info [at] ikmaak [dot] nl</computeroutput
>, based in the Netherlands.) Ruben also carries these stepper motors.</para
></section
><section
><title
>Hardware kits</title
><para
>These kits contain all rods, bolts, nuts, washers and springs required to build your printer. Usually they do not include the hardware for the extruder. Neither do they usually included the 608 bearings. Check out these vendors for hardware kits:</para
><itemizedlist
><listitem
><para
>2printbeta.de (based in Germany): <ulink
url="http://www.2printbeta.de/product_info.php?products_id=42"
>nuts &amp; bolts kit</ulink
> and <ulink
url="http://www.2printbeta.de/product_info.php?products_id=41"
>rods kit</ulink
></para
></listitem
><listitem
><para
>xyzprinters.com (based in the Netherlands): <ulink
url="http://www.xyzprinters.com/nuts-bolts/93-prusa-mendel-nuts-bolts-kit-88-bzp.html"
>nuts &amp; bolts kit</ulink
> and <ulink
url="http://www.xyzprinters.com/rods-bars/139-prusa-threaded-rod-kit-88-bzp.html"
>rods kit</ulink
></para
></listitem
><listitem
><para
>You can also check <ulink
url="http://www.emakershop.com/browse/vitamins"
>eMAKERshop</ulink
> or ebay for vendors. Beware however of kits that contain nuts &amp; bolts, belts and printer parts; on many occassions these turn out more expensive than the sum of the parts.</para
></listitem
></itemizedlist
><para
>Ask the vendors In case you are not certain whether or not their hardware kits include all the items on the RepRap Prusa Mendel <ulink
url="http://reprap.org/wiki/Prusa_Mendel"
>BOM</ulink
>.</para
><sidebar
><title
>Warning on LM8UU metal linear bearings</title
><para
>LM8UU metal linear bearings require your smooth rods to be made from rolled steel. Anything softer than rolled steel will get damaged by the linear bearings and might also damage the linear bearings. Very few kits however provide rolled steel smooth bars. For this reason LM8UU metal linear bearings can drive the price of your printer up significantly.</para
></sidebar
></section
><section
><title
>Extruder</title
><para
>The printed parts for the Wade’s geared extruder are usually part of the printed parts kit but be sure to double-check. You will probably has to buy a separate Wade's geared extruder hardware kit. These vendors sell them:</para
><itemizedlist
><listitem
><para
><ulink
url="http://www.2printbeta.de/product_info.php?products_id=54"
>2printbeta.de</ulink
> (based in Germany)</para
></listitem
><listitem
><para
><ulink
url="http://www.xyzprinters.com/nuts-bolts/119-wade-nuts-bolts-kit.html"
>xyzprinters.com</ulink
> (based in the Netherlands)</para
></listitem
></itemizedlist
></section
><section
><title
>Kapton tape</title
><para
>Kapton tape is a space-age product. It's tape that can resist the high temperatures typically found around a RepRap 3D Printer. Kapton tape must be put on a heated bed (the filament won't stick to the heated bed itself) and optionally also on the hotend. You will need two widths of kapton tape: 1cm and 5cm. A roll of kapton tape typically holds about 33m. Check the vendors mentioned above for kapton tape, also check ruben-ikmaak (<computeroutput
>info [at] ikmaak [dot] nl</computeroutput
>, based in the Netherlands.)</para
></section
></section
></article
>
