<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.1//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.1/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>How the printer works</title>
  </articleinfo>

  <para>This 3D printer builds objects by adding plastic material layer by
  layer until the object (also called printed part) is finished. The printer
  has a frame and three axes: X-axis (moves left-to-right), Y-axis (moves
  front-to-back) and Z-axis (moves up-and-down.) The
  <emphasis>extruder</emphasis> sits on the X-axis and feeds and melts plastic
  <emphasis>filament</emphasis>. The lowest part of the extruder is the
  <emphasis>extruder head</emphasis>, here the plastic is melted and
  <emphasis>extruded</emphasis> through a tiny hole with a diameter of less
  than 1mm. To print objects the electronics of the printer steer the three
  axes so that the extruder head is at the right spot to add plastic to the
  printed part. The three axes together with the extruder is called the
  <emphasis>Cartesian robot</emphasis>.</para>

  <para>The printer is usually controlled by a PC with special software
  installed. In this software a solid model is loaded (these are called STL
  files) that gets converted to G-code<footnote>
      <para>G-code is a standard language for CNC machines that consists of a
      sequence of movement commands.</para>
    </footnote>.This G-code is sent to the electronics over USB and tells the
  robot what movements to make. At the end of all of these movements the
  modelled part should have been printed. Alternatively the same software can
  convert the model to G-code and save these codes on a SD-card. If the
  electronics of your printer is equipped with a SD-card reader you can print
  parts without the need to have a PC connected during the entire print
  job.</para>

  <sidebar>
    <title>Introduction video</title>

    <para>This is a good time to watch the excellent 15 minute <ulink
    url="http://tinyurl.com/prusa-intro">introduction video</ulink> on the
    RepRap Prusa Mendel 3D printer.</para>
	<?dbhtml-include href="ohmeye_video.html"?>
  </sidebar>
</article>
