<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.1//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.1/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Introduction</title>
  </articleinfo>

  <para>Home-built 3D printers are booming. In 2006 there were no such
  printers and 5 years later there are tens of thousands. There are currently
  hundreds of thousands of people wanting to start their own build waiting for
  the right moment to get started.</para>

  <para>The project that single-handily propelled home-built 3D printers out
  of nowhere is RepRap. It’s an open-source project meaning that all the
  information and design plans you’ll need are available free for all.
  Building a 3D printer yourself is a huge undertaking. You can build it for
  less than $500 or €500 but months might go by between getting started and
  printing your first part.</para>

  <para>Building a 3D printer is very hands-on and will require all your
  technical skills. There isn’t really any void that needs to be filled since
  there are enough people and good information online to answer your questions
  and help you out. Still there hasn’t yet appeared one book that guides you
  through building your own 3D printer. </para>

  <para>These are the sections of this book:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>How a RepRap 3D printer works</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Parts of the printer</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>A word on the most commonly used plastics</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Tools and skills required</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Software required to run a RepRap 3D printer</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Buyer’s guide</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Links to build instructions</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>This book is not a replacement for build instructions. There are
  excellent and unambiguous build instructions available in written form, as
  visual instructions and videos. Instead this book has been designed to
  prepare you before you start building.</para>

  <mediaobject id="image1">
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/working_prusa.jpg" />
    </imageobject>

    <caption><para>Image 1: a working RepRap Prusa Mendel 3D printer (<ulink
    url="http://reprap.org/wiki/File:Assembled-prusa-mendel.jpg">source</ulink>)</para></caption>
  </mediaobject>

  <para><link linkend="image1">Image 1</link> shows a fully assembled working
  home-built 3D printer. It is called RepRap Prusa Mendel and it is the
  printer this book will help you to build yourself. It costs about $500 or
  €500 in parts. You can buy this printer as a kit but then you will pay at
  least double this price. Many people source the individual parts themselves
  and once they receive them get started on their build.</para>
</article>
