Parts of the printerFrameImage 2: empty RepRap Prusa Mendel frame. Notice the various printed parts that keep the frame together. (source)
The frame gives the printer its stiffness. The three axes of the robot will be added to this frame. The frame consists of threaded rods connected together with printed parts (these are called the vertices.)
RepRap: the printer that can print its own partsThe Rep in RepRap stands for reproduction. RepRap printers are designed in such a way that they can print their own parts. As soon as you’ve got your printer working you can print parts for a new printer or you can start printing various improvements on the standard design. RepRap owners regularly sell the printed parts required to build new printers on ebay.
Apart from the vertices the frame also contains printed parts to hold and control the Y-axis and Z-axis. On the top left and top right you can see the printed parts that will hold the stepper motors of the Z-axis.
Image 3: RepRap Prusa Mendel frame with smooth rods for Y-axis and Z-axis mounted (source)
Onimage 3you can see the frame with the smooth rods added for the Y-axis (the horizontal rods) and the Z-axis (the vertical rods.)
Y-axis and bushingsImage 4: RepRap Prusa Mendel frame with Y-axis installed (source)
Onimage 4you see the print bottom plate assembled on the Y-axis smooth rods. The Y-axis has one degree of freedom: it can move between the front and the back of the frame. The Y-axis is controlled by a belt attached to a stepper motor with pulley that you can also see on the image. The print bottom plate has four bushings attached that have been glued to the print bottom plate.
The RepRap axes - like many CNC machines - move over smooth rods with bushings or more recently with linear bearings.
Bushings are actually plain bearings. They slide over smooth rods and provide almost no friction when moving up and down the rods. Usually plain bearings are used to turn around a cylinder (or to have the cylinder turn inside.) On the RepRap the bushings don’t turn, instead they linearly move up and down the smooth rods following an imaginary line on the rods.
Linear bearings have little balls inside and provide free motion in one direction. Both bushings and linear bearings can be either printed or sourced as metal parts. Metal bushings are made from brass as it's the only metal that has low friction and is self-lubricating. RepRap designs that use linear bearings typically use LM8UU metal bearings. The standard RepRap Prusa Mendel design uses bushings that are more than good enough for the purpose. Some people believe a RepRap printer looks more cool when fitted with LM8UU linear bearings (but this drives up the price.)
Home-made 3D printers are meant to be customizedIf you would like linear bearings on your printer then by all means go ahead and print the partsYou can find the X-axis parts with linear bearings for a RepRap Prusa Mendelhere.
!
Image 5: brass bushings inserted in printed parts (source)
Image 6: printed linear bearing (source)
Some people use felt bushings. These are printed bushings with a small piece of felt glued inside the bushings. Felt cloth moves very smoothly over a smooth bar.Image 7below shows a printed part with felt bushings:
Image 7: felt bushings glued on a printed part (source)
Z-axis and Y-axisImage 8: RepRap Prusa Mendel frame with X-axis, Y-axis and Z-axis installed (source)
Onimage 8you can see a RepRap Prusa Mendel frame with Y-axis, Z-axis and X-axis assembled. The Z-axis and Y-axis are actually part of one construction. The Z-axis moves the X-axis up and down the frame. The X-axis moves the extruder left and right within the frame.
Image 9: X-end idler part on the left-hand side, X-end motor part on the right-hand side (source unknown)
The Z-and-X axis construction consists of two printed parts called the X-end idler (leftimage 9) and X-end motor (rightimage 9). The X-end idler has two vertical sections: a square open box and a hexagon structure. In the square open box two bushings are glued. This box serves as a guide for the vertical smooth rod. In the hexagon structure two M8 bolts and a spring are mounted. A threaded rod is turned into these bolts. This threaded rod is also connected to the stepper motor on the top of the frame. The stepper motor will turn the threaded rod around its axis that in turn will make the X-end idler move up and down. You can see the assembled X-end idler onimage 10:
Image 10: assembled X-end idler (source)
The X-end motor has the same two sections and is assembled in a similar way. As you’ve noticed on the images the Z-axis is controlled by two stepper motors. It turns out it’s both cheaper and improves accuracy to have two stepper motors on the Z-axis instead of one motor and a belt (mainly because the later requires a much more complicated construction and an expensive belt.) The Y-axis and X-axis are controlled by one motor and a belt, here two motors don’t make sense.
ExtruderThe RepRap Prusa Mendel is typically equiped with a Wade’s geared extruderYou can find the designs for the Wade's geared extruderhere
. This extruder consists of two parts: a cold top part that feeds the platic filament and a hot bottom part that melts and extrudes the plastic. These two parts are commonly called the Wade extruder (the cold part) and the hot-end (the hot part).
Image 11: Wade's geared extruder (source)
The Wade extruder consists of a large gear that is driven by a stepper motor. This large gear drives a bolt that pulls the plastic filament and pushes it into the hot-end where the plastic melts.
The hot-end is usually a brass bolt with a hole drilled down its vertical axis. This screw is called a heater barrel. There are two sizes of filament available: 3mm wide and 1.75mm wide. The hole drilled in your heater barrel will have to match the size of your filament! At the tip of the heat barrel the exit hole narrows down to less than 1mm (typically 0.5mm.)
Two methods exist for heating the hot-end: using a resistor or using a NiChrome wire. A NiChrome wire is the easiest to get started since you will only need a heater barrel with a nozzle. A resistor requires a heater block that is screwed onto the heater barrel.
Image 12shows a heater block with a resistor installed. The heater block is screwed into a heater barrel:
Image 12: heater block with resistor installed (source)
Image 13shows a heater barrel wrapped with NiChome wire:
Image 13: heater barrel wrapped with NiChrome wire (the assembly shown in this image is not finished) (source)
A hot-end has three more crucial components: a thermistor to measure the temperature, a heat barrier to separate the hot-end from the cold-end (without this the cold-end would melt) and the nozzle where the melted plastic flows out of the heater barrel.
The thermistor is connected to the electronics board - just like the resistor or NiChrome wire - and allows the electronics to measure and regulate the temperature of the heater barrel. The heater barrel operates at a configurable temperature, without the thermistor that temperature could not be reached and held.
The heat barrier prevents the heat from the heater barrel to rise to the cold part. The cold part consists of printed parts and these would melt if they became too hot. Typically PEEK is used as a heat barrier. PEEK can resist high temperature and transfers very little heat. PEEK however has a number of disadvantages: it’s not easy to find in the format suitable for use on an extruder, it’s pretty expensive as well and it requires a PFTE tube inside to help the flow of filament. PFTE tube can be difficult to find as well.
At least one person has assembled an extruder where PEEK and PFTE was replaced with a piece of bambooInstructions for bamboo as heat barrierhere.
. Bamboo has the same properties as PEEK: resists high temperature and transfers very little heat. It is however much cheaper and much easier to find.
The nozzle is the most important part of the hot-end. The nozzle is the end of the heater barrel where the melted plastic is extruded. The nozzle needs to have a sharp enough tip and a central hole that is less than 1mm (typically 0.5mm.)Image 14shows a heater barrel with nozzle:
Image 14: a heater barrel. Suitable for either NiChrome wire or heater block (source)
X-carriageThe assembled extruder - including cold-end, heat barrier and hot-end - is mounted on the X-axis carriage.Image
    15below shows an assembled X-axis with two smooth rods, the X-end idler and X-end motor printed parts and the printed X-carriage:
Image 15: assembled X-axis with two smooth rods, the X-end idler and X-end motor printed parts and the printed X-carriage (source)
The X-carriage can use bushings or linear bearings. The X-carriage is controlled by one stepper motor and a belt.Image 16shows an assembled Wade’s geared extruder mounted on the X-carriage. Notice the belt in the background.
Image 16: assembled Wade's geared extruder mounted on the X-carriage. Notice the belt in the background (source)
Print platePrinted parts are printed on the print plate. The three axes move together so that the nozzle can move above the print plate in an area of 200mm wide by 200mm deep by 100mm high.
The print plate actually consists of two plates: the print bottom plate that is mounted on the X-axis smooth rods with bushings or linear bearings and the print top plate that is mounted on the bottom plate and that forms the print surface.
The top print plate must be level! The top print plate is mounted with fours springs slid over four screws so that it can be easily adjusted.Image 17shows both print plates one stacked on top of the other. The springs are clearly visible. The bottom print plate is mounted on the X-axis smooth rods with printed bushings.
Image 17: top print plate stack on bottom print plate. The springs are clearly visible. The bottom print plate is mounted on the X-axis smooth rods with printed bushings (source)
A popular add-on for your printer is the heated bed. These significantly reduce the amount ofwarpingon printed parts, especially on the lower layers. Warping is caused by the uneven cooling of outer and inner sections of a printed part. The material at the outside of a part will cool and thus shrink faster than the material inside. This will cause the cooler material towarpor bend while the hot material won’tSee this excellentguidefor more details on warping
. This uneven shrinking will cause straight edges to bend and might cause structural failure in parts. Warping is especially a problem for the lower layers of a part since the print plate will cool those layers much faster than higher layers.
The bottom section of the left-hand part onimage 18below clearly shows warping while the identical right-hand part doesn’t:
Image 18: left-hand part clearly shows warping in bottom section (source)
The solution is to print on a heated bed so that the entire lower section of a part is kept at the same temperature. A heatbed can heat the top print plate up to 100C.Image 19shows a heatbed installed on a RepRap Prusa Mendel printer.
Image 19: heatbed mounted on RepRap Prusa Mendel top print plate (source)
Usually the heatbed is turned off after the first ten or so layers have been printed. This way the lower section of the printed part can cool down evenly together with the heatbed while the remained of the part is still being printed. A heatbed can either be bought or home-made. Buying is of course easier but building it yourself is feasible and cheaperSee theseinstructionsfor building your own heatbed
. When you install a heatbed be sure to check the temperature of the transistor on your electronics board. If it gets very hot you might have to install a little heat sink (you can find those very cheap on ebay or in your local electronics shop.)
Warning on installing heat sinksWhenever you install a heat sink on any electronic component always put heat paste between the component and the heat sink. With heat paste the component and heat sink will warm up more or less evenly. Without heat paste the component won’t be able to transfer the majority of its heat to the heat sink (air transfers heat poorly.) You can find heat paste cheaply on ebay. Never use glue instead of heat paste!
ElectronicsThe electronics board controls the printing process. Several electronics options exist for RepRap printers (they are all open-source.) Currently the most popular are:

- RAMPS, a DIY shield board for Arduino MEGA

- Sanguinololu, an all-in-one DIY board with microprocessor on board

The RepRap electronics board has several functions:

- Process G-code instructions.

- Control the four stepper motor controllers (there are five stepper motors on a RepRap Prusa Mendel but both Z-axis motors are connected to the same stepper motor controller.)

- Control the temperature of the hot-end and monitor the hot-end thermistor.

- Monitor the end-stops (end-stops are used for homing the three axes, see later section.)

- Control the temperature of the heated bed and monitor the heated bed thermistor (the heated bed is optional.)

The electronics board is connected to the PC using a USB-to-serial converter. The Arduino used with the RAMPS board has such a converter built-in, so does the Sanguinololu board.
The RAMPS electronics board has been around longer than the Sanguinololu and has seen regular updates. RAMPS is a shield board that needs to be connected to an Arduino MEGA 1280 or 2560 board (or a clone board.) The RAMPS has these additional features:

- One extra heater / thermistor channel (three in total)

- Optional SD card reader

Image 20shows a RAMPS board mounted on a Arduino MEGA board with four Pololu stepper motor controller boards installed:
Image 20: an assmebled RAMPS board mounted on a Arduino MEGA board with four Pololu stepper motor controller boards installed (source)
The Sanguinololu board is a more recent addition. It doesn’t offer the extra thermal channel of the RAMPS and connecting an SD reader is more difficult. However, all electronics are contained on one board and hence doesn’t require an Arduino MEGA board. This makes the Sanguinololu cheaper than the RAMPS. A complete RAMPS DIY kit including Arduino MEGA clone and four Pololu stepper controllers will typically cost about $100 or €100. A complete Sanguinololu DIY kit will typically only cost about $80 or €80.
A few things have to be taken into account though. When building your own Sanguinololu you will have to solder a very small chipInstructionson how to solder the small chip on the Sanguinololu board
(the USB-to-serial bridge). Also, you should make sure the ATMega microprocessor comes with the Sanguinololu boot loader installed. If this is not the case you will have to install this boot loader yourself and that is pretty complicatedSee theseinstructionsfor loading the Sanguinololu boot loader
. Ask your vendor in case you are not sure whether or not the bootloader is pre-loaded.
Although both the RAMPS and Sanguinololu boards have been designed to be assembled by hand the PCB’s cannot be etched at home. Actually, the Sanguinololu board can’t be etched at home at all, RAMPS boards versions 1.25 or earlier can be etched at home with some tweaksSeeherefor details on how to etch a RAMPS board yourself
.
If you want to follow the path of least resistance you should go for a RAMPS board. But maybe you like the Sanguinololu’s small size and lower price.Image 21shows an assembled Sanguinololu board with four Pololu stepper controller boards installed:
Image 21: assembled Sanguinololu board with four Pololy stepper controller boards installed (source)
Stepper motorsThere are five stepper motors on the RepRap Prusa Mendel:

- One to control the Y-axis

- One to control the X-axis

- Two to control the Z-axis

- One to control the extruder

Normally all five motors on a printer are the same but this is not required except for the two motors that control the Z-axis: these must be identical. The RepRap Prusa Mendel has been designed to use bipolar NEMA17 motors. NEMA17 determines some of the dimensions of a stepper motor.
Image 22: the internals of a stepper motor (source)
Not every NEMA17 motor is equalThe most important aspect of a stepper motor is its torque. However, the amount of torque the motor will actually supply is also determined by the stepper controller board.
A stepper motor is a special kind of electric motor that is often used in robotics. The motor has two sets of internal coils positioned around a central teethed shaft that contains a permanent magnet. Each set of coils is part of a phase. The coils the belong to the same phase will generate magnetic fields with the same North-South orientation. The motors used on RepRap Prusa Mendel printers have two phases. The RepRap electronics board controls the stepper through micro-stepping. In this mode the percentage of current is gradually changed per phase to make the shaft rotate in small stepsThis
        appletdemonstrates how micro-stepping works inside a stepper motor (note: the stepper motor shown in this applet is unipolar while RepRap uses bipolar motors. The principles however remain the same.)
.
Stepper motor controllersControlling a bipolar stepper motor is pretty complicated, especially in micro-stepping mode. Unipolar stepper motors are easier to control but they offer less torque for the same motor size. Special stepper motor controllers have been developed that take over the complexities of controlling a stepper motor. With such a controller one only needs to send one signal to make one micro-step. This seriously simplifies controlling the stepper motor.
The RepRap community has chosen to use Pololu stepper motor controllers. These come in the form of a small board with one IC - the Pololu stepper motor controller - and a few passive components. Pololu offers both the IC and the board. This board uses very small components so has to be factory assembled. In late 2010 Pololu was experiencing difficulties to ship enough boards so RepRap community member Joem decided to design an open-source version of this board calledStepStick. This board still uses the Pololu IC that never was is short supply. One assembled StepStick board usually costs about $10 or €10. Four StepStick boards are required for a RepRap Prusa Mendel printer.
Warning about StepStick boardRepRap community members have reported StepStick boards with short-circuits in them! Obviously this might destroy both your StepStick board and your electronics board. Before installing a StepStick board always verify with your multi-meter there are not short-circuits on the pins.
When stepper motors are in operation and stand still they still use current. For this reason each stepper motor controller has a potentiometer to control how much current is sent to the stepper. If you send too much current you might use more current than is required (and hence increase your electricity bill.)
For this reason is it advised to close the potentiometer on each stepper motor controller by turning counter-clockwise all the way and then open the potentiometer about ¼ th of the way. When you discover one of your steppers does not provide enough torque you can open the potentiometer of that stepper motor controller at little bit further.
End stopsAt the start of a print job all three axes have to be moved to their starting or homing position. This is the zero position of the Cartesian robot. The axes can’t move any further than zero (they can’t move to a negative position.)
To achieve this three end stops need to be installed, one for each axis. A end stop needs to be installed at the position where the axis shouldn’t move beyond:

- For the X-axis this should be the position where the nozzle reaches the left-hand side of the print plate.

- For the Y-axis this should be on the back-side of the axis so that the print plate is moved to the back far enough that the nozzle ends up on the forward of the print plate.

- For the Z-axis this should be the position where the nozzle barely touches the print plate. When printing the software will make sure the Z-axis is lifted a little before printing the first layer.

When to position your endstopsPosition your endstops correctly after you've calibrated your X-Y-and-Z axes. After calibration the command "move 1mm" will actually move one mm. Before calibration you can't be certain where your axis will end up.
You can choose between two kinds of end stops: optical or mechanical switch. The mechanical switches are preferred since they are much cheaper, easier to install and work just as well as optical end stops.
Mechanical vs. optical endstopsSwitches have a limited number of on/off cycles. However, most purpose built micro-switches are rated for well over 10,000 cycles and will last yearsSource
. Optical endstops are on paper more reliable than mechanical endstops but in practice they are not (todo: discuss.) You should go for mechanical endstops.
End stops are not required at the opposite ends. Thefirmwareyou will install in the microprocessor knows how far each axis is allowed to move calculated from position zero. These distances can be configured.
Image 23: an assembled optical end stop PCB (source)
Image 24shows a mechanical end stop mounted on the Z-axis. Notice the nozzle in the background is hovering a few centimeter above the print plate meaning the X-end idler part is positioned just a little bit to high to be in this picture. From the nozzle and print plate positions one can also deduce the X-axis and Y-axis must be in (or near) position zero. The front of the printer frame is to the right in this image.
Image 24: mechanical end stop mounted on Z-axis (source)
