<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.1//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.1/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>RepRap software</title>
  </articleinfo>

  <para>A RepRap printer is judged by the quality of the objects it has
  printed and secondarily the speed with which these objects can be printed.
  The quality of the prints is determined in part by the quality of your
  mechanical build. Another important contributor to print quality or lack
  thereof is the software you use with your RepRap and how it has been
  configured. The fundamental pieces of software required to run a RepRap
  printer are discussed here.</para>

  <para>You will need at least four applications installed on your computer to
  run a RepRap Prusa Mendel 3D printer. They are:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Arduino software</emphasis>: this
      application allows you to install the printer firmware onto the ATMega
      microprocessor. This installation is required each time you want to
      update the firmware. </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Firmware</emphasis>: there are several
      firmwares available for RepRap printers. The firmware is installed on
      the ATMega microprocessor and handles the G-code instructions received
      from the PC. Part of the configuration of the printer has to be done in
      the firmware.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Skein software</emphasis>: the most popular
      application to slice STL files into G-code is called Skeinforge. You
      need this piece of software each time you want to print a part.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Host software</emphasis>: there are also
      several host application available for RepRap printers. This application
      is responsible for communicating with the electronics of the printer
      before and during print jobs. It prepares the printer before starting a
      print job and then also starts the actual print jobs.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>These applications are discussed in turn below.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Arduino software for RAMPS</title>

    <para>For the RAMPS electronics you need to follow the instructions for
    installing the Arduino environment:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.arduino.cc/en/Guide/Windows">Windows
        installation instructions</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.arduino.cc/en/Guide/MacOSX">Mac OS X
        installation instructions</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://www.arduino.cc/playground/Learning/Linux">Linux
        installation instructions</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <sidebar>
      <title>COM port to communicate with your Arduino board</title>

      <para>Make sure to remember or write down the COM port to which your
      Arduino is connected. </para>
    </sidebar>

    <para>Once the Arduino board is connected to the Arduino software you can
    skip ahead to the firmware section.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Arduino software for Sanguinololu</title>

    <para>For the Sanguinololu board you will need to follow these Sanguino
    installation instructions:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://sanguino.cc/softwareforwindows">Windows
        installation instructions</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://sanguino.cc/softwareformac">Mac OS X
        installation instructions</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://sanguino.cc/softwareforlinux">Linux
        installation instructions</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <sidebar>
      <title>COM port to communicate with your Sanguinololu board</title>

      <para>Make sure to remember or write down the COM port to which your
      Samguinololu is connected.</para>
    </sidebar>

    <para>Once the Sanguinololu board is connected to the Arduino software you
    can follow the instructions in the firmware section.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Firmware</title>

    <para>There are a few popular firmwares available for RepRap 3D
    printers<footnote>
        <para>See also the <ulink
        url="http://reprap.org/wiki/Firmware">list</ulink> of all available
        firmwares for RepRap printers.</para>
      </footnote>. They are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="https://github.com/kliment/Sprinter">Sprinter</ulink>: modern
        firmware with support for SD cards and easy configuration</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="https://github.com/triffid/Teacup_Firmware">Teacup</ulink>:
        claimed to be faster than Sprinter, more elaborate configuration
        options</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Teacup is a decent alternative for Sprinter. However, because of its
    easier configuration we advise you to get started with Sprinter.</para>
  </section>
</article>
