<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.1//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.1/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Tools and skills</title>
  </articleinfo>

  <para>You don’t need to be an electronics buff or mechanical engineer in
  order to build your own 3D printer. If you can screw a nut on a bolt you can
  build this printer.</para>

  <para>You also don’t need to invest large amounts of money in either parts
  or tools. The RepRap has been designed around commonly available parts and
  using commonly available tools.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Mechanical build</title>

    <para>For the mechanical build you will need these tools and the
    associated skills.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Wrenches and keys</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Open end wrenches: M8, M4 and M3</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Hex keys if you’ve bought those kinds of screws</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Digital caliper</title>

      <para>You can't build a RepRap and make it work without a digital
      caliper. If you have a normal caliper put it to the side and order a
      digital caliper. The digital caliper gives a readout of two significant
      digits after the comma. The digital caliper is required while
      calibrating your frame and later when calibrating your axes. You can
      find reliable digital calipers on Amazon for $10 or €10.</para>

      <mediaobject id="image26">
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/digital_caliper.jpg" />
        </imageobject>

        <caption><para>Image 26: Toolzone digital caliper (<ulink
        url="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B001W99N6U/ref=ox_sc_act_title_1?ie=UTF8&amp;m=A3DL2PD92D06B0">source</ulink>)</para></caption>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>There are two important tidbits to remember about digital
      calipers:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>When storing away your digital caliper always remove the
          battery. These devices never really shut down.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Whenever you make a measurement always first reset your
          caliper to zero, even when it already says
          <computeroutput>00,0</computeroutput>. If you make measurement
          without resetting the caliper to zero you might get inaccurate
          readings.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Despite these two small annoyances digital calipers outperform
      regular calipers in such a way that you can't build a RepRap printer
      without them.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Spirit level</title>

      <para>A spirit level is used during frame building, axes building and
      general calibration of your printer. A smaller spirit level is better
      than a bigger:</para>

      <mediaobject id="image27">
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/spirit_level.jpg" />
        </imageobject>

        <caption><para>Image 27: Draper spirit level (<ulink
        url="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Draper-Tools-DIY-Pocket-Level/dp/B002V9X424">source</ulink>)</para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Plumb line</title>

      <para>You need a plumb line a one point only during the build: when the
      Z-axis smooth rods are installed. You can also hang a nut on a string
      but a plumb line will work much better.</para>

      <mediaobject id="image28">
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/plumb_line.jpg" />
        </imageobject>

        <caption><para>Image 27: Draper plumb line (<ulink
        url="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Silverline-Plumb-Bob-Line/dp/B002QRYEEI/">source</ulink>)</para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Installation of Z-axis bushings</title>

      <para>Depending on which kinds of bushings you're using you need
      different kinds of tools. There a there really two categories:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Seperate bushings like PLA bushings or printed bushing holders
          for brass bushings</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Bushings integrated into the printed parts. This is generally
          referred to as the Prusa <emphasis>felt branch</emphasis>. This is
          actually a counter-intuitive name. The designer of the RepRap Prusa
          Mendel printer - Josef Prusa - created a <emphasis>branch</emphasis>
          with bushing holders integrated in the printed parts. The original
          purpose was to glue small pieces of felt into these holders (felt
          was then used as a bushing.) It is also possible to mount brass
          bushings in these holder. Later on the parts for LM8UU bearings were
          also added to this branch. The use of felt as a bushing never really
          caught on and is now outdated. The bushing holders integrated into
          the parts are still popular for use with brass bushings and LM8UU
          linear bearings.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>
